Guide to the Letters to Ernst Curtius and Ernst Robert Curtius, 1841-1956.
Letters to Ernst Curtius and Ernst Robert Curtius
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Letters to Ernst Curtius and Ernst Robert Curtius, 1841-1956.
6957
Ernst, Curtius 1814-1896.
1 cubic foot (circa 140 items).
Correspondence, Manuscripts
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Letters to Ernst Curtius and Ernst Robert Curtius, covering the period 1841-1956
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Ernst Curtius (1814-1896) was an eminent philologist and archeologist. From 1844-50 he served as tutor ("Zivilgouverneur") to Prince Friedrich von Hohenzollern, afterwards Emperor Friedrich III. He was also professor of classical philology, archeology, and eloquence at the Universities of Göttingen and Berlin. In 1874 Curtius concluded an agreement with the Greek authorities by which the excavations in Olympia were entrusted exclusively to the Germans. What he found there ultimately led to the re-institution of the Olympic Games by Baron Pierre de Coubertin in 1894.
His grandson Ernst Robert Curtius (1886-1956) was a foremost literary scholar of the 20th century. The son of high-ranking civil servant, he grew up in Alsace, a French province annexed by the Reich between 1871 and 1918, and was thus bilingual in German and French -- and also fluent in English, Italian, and Spanish. Under the aegis of Strasbourg Professor Gustav Gröber, he devoted his doctoral dissertation to editing an Old French epic, but his "Habilitationsschrift" in Bonn was on the contemporary French critique Ferdinand Brunetière: thus emerged the two paths, i.e. the study of "medieval literature" and the critical appraisal of recent works, that he was to follow throughout his life. Curtius rejected Brunetière’s "scientific" method, instead favoring intuition, attention to nuances, and "elected affinities" as the most meaningful avenues toward literary knowledge. After being mobilized and wounded in Poland during World War I, he obtained a tenured position at the University of Bonn in 1916. Eevn though he considered the politicization of spiritual and intellectual life as a betrayal of the truly independent thinker, his scholarship in the 1920s often seemed to support a political, pan-European agenda: "Der Europagedanke, he would say, mußte geistig gebaut werden. Dazu wollten meine Bücher helfen." Curtius took part in international symposiums in Pontigny (Burgundy) and Colpach (Luxemburg); was in touch with the Austrian prince von Rohan (who had launched an "Europäische Revue" in 1925, and would join join the Nazi Party in 1938); and corresponded with Parisian intellectuals of all stripes, despite the divisions generated by two wars (1870-71, 1914-18). The exchange slowed down considerably after 1933 however, and not only because of the passing of his beloved Catherine Pozzi (1882-1934), a poetess and former lover of Paul Valéry who wrote scientific articles and translated the poetry of Stefan George. Curtius dedicated to her his essay, "James Joyce’s Ulysses" (1929) and also corresponded with Pozzi's son, Claude Bourdet, a young engineer who would become a major figure of the Resistance and create the weekly "L'Observateur" (after 1964 "Le Nouvel Observateur.") In 1931, Catherine Pozzi wrote to Curtius: "In Frankreich scheint das Geistige noch in keiner Gefahr zu stehn, wie bei Ihnen." Indeed, with Hitler leading the new Reich, life became almost impossible for German intellectuals. A fervent patriot and a Stoic, Curtius decided to stay in Germany and to focus on medieval and Renaissance literature, where less political interference would be encountered. Despite his commitment to "European unity" he would reject any "collaboration" between Germany and France after 1940 -- to the disappointment of his admirer Jacques Benoist-Méchin (1901-1983), a brilliant journalist, military historian, and Proust scholar who occupied a number of high positions in the Vichy regime. In 1950, back from the Institute for Advanced Studies at Princeton, Curtius wrote to Anne Heurgon-Desjardins: "Les querelles franco-allemandes m’ennuient. Je considère ces deux peuples comme des collégiens mal élevés qui se chamaillent. J’ai fait métier de rapprocheur pendant vingt ans. J’ai maintenant droit à la retraite."
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
This collection contains about a hundred and fifty letters and some drawings addressed mostly by Parisian intellectuals, poets and scholars to Ernst Curtius and Ernst Robert Curtius, two prominent members of the German educated upper middle-class (Bildungsbürgertum) between 1841 and 1934.
Letters to Ernst Curtius are in series 1.
Letters to Ernst Robert Curtius are in series 2.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Aragon, 1897-1982.; Balzac, Honore´ de, 1799-1850.; Balzac, Honore´ de, 1799-1850--Appreciation--Germany.; Beach, Sylvia.; Benois-Me´chin, Jacques, 1901-; Blanche, Jacques-Emile, 1861-1942.; Bourdet, Claude, 1909-1996.; Cocteau, Jean, 1889-1963.; Coudenhove-Kalergi, Richard Nicolaus, Graf von, 1894-1972.; Curtius, Ernst, 1814-1896.; Curtius, Ernst Robert, 1886-1956.; Crevel, René, 1900-1935.; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321--Appreciation.; Du Bos, Charles, 1882-1939.; George, Stefan Anton, 1868-1933.; Gide, André, 1869-1951.; Green, Julien, 1900-1998.; Joyce, James, 1882-1941.; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955.; Maritain, Jacques, 1882-1973.; Paulhan, Jean, 1884-1968.; Pozzi, Catherine, 1882-1934.; Proust, Marcel, 1871-1922.; Rilke, Rainer Maria, 1875-1926.; Rohan, Karl Anton Prinz, 1898-1975.; Sieburg, Friedrich, 1893-1964.; Thibaudet, Albert, 1874-1936.; Valéry, Paul, 1871-1945.; Action franc¸aise.
Subjects:
Anti-Americanism-- France.; Archaeology.; Biography in literature.; Communism.; Criticism.; De´cades de Pontigny.; European Cooperation--History.; Literature.; National socialism.; National socialism and literature.; National socialism and scholarship.; Philology--Germany--History--19th century.; Philology--History--20th Century; Philology History and criticism.; Politics in Literature.
Places:
France -- Civlization.; Paris (France)-- History.; Vence (France).
Form and Genre Terms:
Correspondence.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
PROVENANCE
The letters were given to the Division of Rare Books and Manuscripts in Kroch Library in 2001 by Mrs. Jane Marsh Dieckmann, widow of Herbert Dieckmann (1906-1986), a professor of Romance Studies at Harvard (1950-66) and Cornell (1966-74.) Born in North Rhine-Westphalia, Herbert Dieckmann wrote his doctorate in Bonn under the direction of Ernst Robert Curtius, and left Germany in 1933. A specialist of Diderot, he spent his last years co-editing and annotating the voluminous correspondence between his former professor and André Gide, Valéry Larbaud, and Charles Du Bos. Letters from other European intellectuals and writers were handed over to the Dieckmann by Ilse Curtius, but not selected for publication -- they form the present collection.
RELATED MATERIALS
"Deutsch-französiche Gespräche, 1920-1950. La Correspondance de Ernst Robert Curtius avec André Gide, Charles du Bos et Valery Larbaud" Herbert et Jane M. Dieckmann ed., Frankfurt am Main: Vittorio Klostermann, 1980.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series 1: Letters from and to Ernst Curtius
  - Hase, Karl Benedict [Curator at the Département des Manuscrits of the Bibliothèque nationale in Paris], to "Monsieur Curtius, Professeur de littérature ancienne à l'Université Royale de Berlin", 30 November 1844; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 1a)
    ALS in German: "Wir gehen einer Zeit entgegen, wo es von der größten Wichtigkeit sein wird, daß der Beherrscher des einzigen waffenmächtigen protestantischen Staates in Europa (England ist keine Landmacht) teutschen Sinn habe, klug und fest sei, gleich entfernt von Gleichgültigkeit für das Höchste und von befangener Frömmelei. Und kann irgend etwas in Ihrem Zögling solche Gefühle wecken, solche Eigenschaften entwickeln, so sind es gewiß Ihre Lehren und Ihr Beispiel.".
  - Hase, Karl Benedict [Curator at the Département des Manuscrits of the Bibliothèque nationale in Paris], to "Monsieur Curtius, Professeur de littérature ancienne à l'Université Royale de Berlin", 2 July 1845; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 1b)
    ALS in German: "Bedenken Sie, verehrtester Freund, wie wichtig es für das Wohl eines ganzen Landes ist dass dessen künftiger Herrscher nicht bloß Hofstaat und Hofprediger um sich habe, sondern auch Männer voll Geist, Wissenschaft und Verstand, teutsch gesinnt, vertraut mit den großen Alten."
  - Curtius, Ernst, to Theodor Heinrich Travers, 14 November 1845; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 1c)
    ALS in German about his position as tutor and preceptor of Kronprinz Friedrich Wilhelm: "Der Prinz entwickelt sich körperlich und geistig zu seinem Vortheile, sein Umgang wird auch für mich immer angenehmer, meine Tätigkeit immer geistiger und würdiger; er geht in sein 13. Jahr, ist aber von meiner Größe, stark und gesund. Im Sommer besuchte ich mit ihm meine Heimat [Lübeck], dann lebten wir auf dem schönen Babelsberger Schlosse [...] bis um Ende Oktober"; also about his academic and social life in Berlin ("Berlin ist jetzt ein ganz anderer Ort geworden, statt des früheren flauen Indifferentismus in allen öffentlichen Dingen ist es jetzt der Ort lebendigen Bewegungen geworden, die durch das ganze Reich pulsieren"); about his friendship with playwright and librettist Emanuel Geibel (1815-1884): "Auch lese ich wieder an der Universität. [...] Dieser Augenblick ist auch Geibel wieder hier, körperlich sehr leidend, aber innerlich sehr produktiv; er schreibt u.A. auch eine Oper jetzt für Mendelssohn [...] Von seinen Gedichten wird die 5. Auflage gedruckt; er steht recht gut"; finally, about his travel projects: "Ich habe entschieden die Absicht, nach Beendigung meiner jetzigen Stellung -- kleine 3 1/2 Jahre -- eine Reise nach Italien und Griechenland zu machen."
  - Laborde, Léon de [Curator of the Départment de Antiquités at the Louvre], to Ernst Curtius, 28 August 1844; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 2)
    ALS in French.
  - Luynes, Honoré d'Albert de [Archeologist and Numismatist], to Ernst Curtius, 27 January 1845; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rochette, Raoul [Curator at the Cabinet des Médailles of the Bibliothèque nationale in Paris], 1841; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 4)
    ALS in French related to his being introduced to Prince Friedrich of Prussia.
  - Rochette, Raoul [Curator at the Cabinet des Médailles of the Bibliothèque nationale in Paris], 11 May 1846; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 5)
    ALS in French: "Vous êtes, Monsieur, du petit nombre des philologues allemands qui joignent à l'étude de la langue, base essentielle de toute connaissance sérieuse de l'Antiquité, le goût et l'intelligence des monuments."
- Series 2: Letters to Ernst Robert Curtius
  - Aragon, Louis, to E.R.Curtius, 4 May 1921; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 6)
    ALS in German about the poor reception of his poetry in France: "Ich schwöre Ihnen, [dass] kein französicher Kritik, dem ich mein Buch gesendet habe, mir ein einfaches Dankwort geschrieben hat". Offers to send Curtius a copy of "Feu de Joie": "Ich würde zufrieden sein, es Ihnen [zu] senden. Hier aber, hielt man es für unverständliches Pathos, und dafür wage ich nicht selbt diese Jugend- (was sage ich?), [diese] Kindheit-Gedichte jemandem zu geben."
  - Aragon, Louis, to E.R. Curtius, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 7)
    ALS in French ("Je crois, Monsieur, que bous ne goûtez guère mes manières de lycéen avec la langue allemande") about his detestation of "literary nationalism."
  - Bainville, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [1932]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bardoux, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, 15 March 1932; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Baroja, Pio, to E.R. Curtius, 27 June 1924; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 10)
    ALS in Spanish.
  - Beach, Sylvia, to E.R. Curtius, 21 December 1928; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 11)
    ALS in English, about James Joyce (his recent books and problems with his eyes.)
  - Beach, Sylvia, to E.R. Curtius, 6 May 1930; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [1922]; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 13)
    ALS in French. B-M. offers to meet in Marburg, rather than France; he’s ashamed of the decadence of his country, doesn’t want to wear the French uniform when they meet.
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, 27 November 1922; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [Summer1923]; 13 leaves (Box 1, Folder 15)
    ALS in French about Claudel, Valéry, Proust. "France can still produce men like Valéry, but not a Rimbaud or a Lenin."
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [1923]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [1923]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, 9 Oct. 1923; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [end of 1923?]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, 16 February 1924; 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, 2 March 1924; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, 23 May 1924; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, September 1924; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 23)
    ALS in French: "La France est un vieux pays pourri de littérature et de bourgeoisie"
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, January 1925; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, 15 June 1926; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, September 1926; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Benoist-Méchin, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, 3 December1933; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 27)
    ALS in French ("Vous conservez un héritage de piété et de dignité intellectuelles... Le traîner jusqu’à l’autre rive peut-il excéder vos forces, si vous savez que sur l’autre rive, tant d’êtres vous attendent et vous saluent?")
  - Blanche, Jacques-Emile, to E.R. Curtius, 3 January 1927; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Blanche, Jacques-Emile, to E.R. Curtius, 14 August 1928; 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 29)
    ALS in French. Mostly about Marcel Proust.
  - Blanche, Jacques-Emile, to E.R. Curtius, 7 December 1929; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 30)
    ALS in French. About literary critique, Gide, Du Bos...
  - Boillot, Félix, to E.R. Curtius, 7 March 1932; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bourdet, Claude, to E.R. Curtius, 1931; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Bourdet, Claude, to E.R. Curtius, 7 December 1934; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 33)
    ALS in German, written after the passing of his mother [Catherine Pozzi]: "Ja, wir werden Freunde bleiben."
  - Bourdet, Claude, to E.R. Curtius, March 1935; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 34)
    ALS in German, about publishing Catherine Pozzi's poem "Peau d'âme" and the situation in Europe ("dass die Flucht von Hass, von Dummheit und Kulturvernichtung sich nähert, dass sie fast schon da ist, quelle tristesse!")
  - Brémond, Abbé Henri, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [1925]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Brémond, Abbé Henri, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [1926?]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Brunschvicg, Léon, to E.R. Curtius, 28 march 1932; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 37)
    ALS in French, annotated by Curtius in German: "von Brunschvigg [sic], über "Essai sur la France" aufheben!"
  - Cocteau, Jean, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [1924]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 38)
    ALS in French, about the death of Radiguet and the alleged misperception of his work in France ("La France qui juge vite me croit saltimbanque.")
  - Cocteau, Jean, to E.R. Curtius, 22 July 1929; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Cocteau, Jean, to E.R. Curtius, 10 October 1929; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Telegram in French.
  - Crevel, René, to E.R. Curtius, 27 September 1924]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 41)
    ALS in French, mostly about "the Americanization of Europe."
  - Crevel, René, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [1927]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 42)
    ALS in French, mostly about his writing projects.
  - Crevel, René, to E.R. Curtius, July 1928; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 43)
    ALS in French: writing projects; Paul Éluard reads Proust.
  - Crevel, René, to E.R. Curtius, 28 december 1931; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 44)
    ALS in French: "J'aime vos compliments, mais pas ce que vous dites de la Révolution... Notre capitalisme, nos nationalisme, le ridicule pan-européanisme à la Coudenhove-Kalergi ont fait leur preuve. Votre Hitler, notre Action Française se valent -- ne valent pas cher. Si vous avez une minute, dites-moi pourquoi vous traitez ainsi la Révolution. Je ne crois pas au libéralisme."
  - Desjardins, Paul, to E.R. Curtius, 31 July 1923; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Evrard, Eugène, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, 18 March 1932; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Friess, Ruth [wife of Horace L. Friess], to E.R. Curtius, 20 February 1932; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 47)
    ALS in English.
  - Gide, André, to E.R. Curtius, 16 October 1936; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 47b)
    ALS in French: a friendly arranging to meet Curtius in Paris; he will not see him at the gathering arranged by "Charlie D.B." [Charles Du Bos], because he will be in Cuverville for his wedding anniversary; he therefore invites Curtius and his wife to have tea on another day, rue Vaneau, with "Mme Théo [van Rysselberghe]". Gide asks Curtius to give him a phone call "in the morning before 11AM."
  - Green, Julien, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [January 1930]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Green, Julien, to E.R. Curtius, February 1930; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Green, Julien, to E.R. Curtius, August 1930; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Grémillon, Jean, to E.R. Curtius, 17 April 1932; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Lyautey, Inès, to E.R. Curtius, 23 July 1927; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Lyautey, Inès, to E.R. Curtius, 23 August 1934; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Maritain, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, 12 July1935; 4 leaves (Box 1, Folder 54)
    ALS in French: the practice of philosophy, the disciples, Thomas Aquinas...
  - Maritain, Jacques, to E.R. Curtius, 4 August 1935; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 55)
    ALS in French: Dante, Barrès...
  - Massignon, Louis, to E.R. Curtius, 5 November 1932; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 56)
    ALS in French, about "L'Essai sur la France."
  - Morand, Paul, to E.R. Curtius, 10 April 1932; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Nathan, Roger ["L'Europe Nouvelle"], to E.R. Curtius, 21 March 1932; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 1 November 1928; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 59)
    ALS in French, about the concept of European culture.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 15 November 1928; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 5 December 1928; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 61)
    ALS in French, about her literary career ("Je n'ai pas de salon, parce que je n'ai pas de diplomatie.") and her interest in the sciences.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 17 December 1928; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 62)
    ALS in French, about languages, the process of learning...
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 26 December 1928; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 63)
    ALS in French, about creation, dream, the universe...
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, January 1929; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 64)
    ALS in French: New Year greetings, their friendship...
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 23 May 1929; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 65)
    ALS in French: their friendship, Rome and Curtius as "a Roman" ("Adieu, tu, Romane!").
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 3 June 1929; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 66)
    ALS in French: invitation to go together in Dordogne; the relative importance of France and Germany ("On voit très bien que toutes les aventures spirituelles les plus hardies et les plus gênantes pour la collectivité paraissent partir d'Allemagne... Luther est allemand. Nietzsche est allemand. Cette sorte de volonté d'atteindre quelque chose qui transcende, et de l'atteindre envers et contre tout, et de détruire pour cela, s'il le faut, tout le reste, c'est allemand.")
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [ mid-June1929]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 67)
    ALS in French: personalism, freedom...
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 28 June 1929; 4 leaves (Box 1, Folder 68)
    ALS in French, containing fragments of a poetic essay.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 3 July 1929; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 69)
    ALS in French and German: their literary friendship.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 10 July 1929; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 70)
    Prose poem in German.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 13-14 July 1929; 2 leaves + 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 71)
    ALS in French: her social status and social obligations in Paris.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [1923]; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 72)
    ALS in French, with a photographic portrait of C. Pozzi and Paul Valéry, and by two original watercolors by C. Pozzi, showing her country house in Provence.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 26 July 1929; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 73)
    ALS in French: Curtius's "Balzac," the "scientific nature" of his work; with a picture of C. Pozzi as "Séraphitus."
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 12 August 1929; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 74)
    ALS in French about her social life in Paris.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [August or September 1929]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 75)
    ALS in French: philosophical considerations.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 24 September 1929; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 76)
    ALS in French: Hofmannstahl; the political opinions of her son Claude Bourdet ("J'ai un fils de dix-neuf ans. Il est très jeune-français d'aujourd'hui; assez américanisé... travaillant à Zürich et donc en allemand... d'Action Française avec passion... C'est un fait que la jeunesse va en masse à l'A.F. ou au communisme") and her own ("Le rapprochement franco-allemand ne se fera pas par la République [mais] par une politique de droite et par une diplomatie d'Ancien régime.")
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [September 1929]; 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 77)
    ALS in French and English: Baden; her mood and feelings.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [September 1929]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 78)
    ALS in French: the nature of their friendship.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [September 1929]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [September 1929]; 5 leaves (Box 1, Folder 80)
    Tapuscript in French.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 12 September 1929; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 81)
    ALS in French: "L'écriture, c'est l'état le moins acceptable aux techniciens [...] Oui, c'est l'état [de] pythie."
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 15 September 1929; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 82)
    ALS in French, "envoyé des hyper-mondes" (sic).
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 10 October 1929; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 83)
    ALS in French: poems in French, German, and Italian.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 25 October 1929; 1 leaf + 5 leaves (Box 1, Folder 84)
    ALS in French: nature, science, plus corrections on a tatuscript.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, n.d [October 1929?]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 85)
    ALS in French: sonnet addressed by Curtius to C. Pozzi, with her follow-up in verses.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, n.d [October 1929?]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 86)
    ALS in French: flowers and insects.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 29 October 1929; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 87)
    ALS in French about Maurice Barrès.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 8 November 1929; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 88)
    ALS in French: about the possibility of translating poems by Stefan George (at Paulhan's request.)
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 30 November 1929; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 89)
    ALS in French: Paulhan's "betrayal."